<data> 
 
	<Default> 
		<header> 
			<title>BALANCE</title> 
			<subtitle>2010 budget</subtitle> 
			<back>RETURN TO MAIN</back> 
			<compare>COMPARE YOUR FIGURES</compare> 
		</header> 
	</Default> 
	
	<SplashPage> 
		<title>BALANCE DEFICIT</title> 
		<subtitle><![CDATA[How would you deal with our...]]></subtitle> 
		<pretitle><![CDATA[New York City's 2010 Budget Game]]></pretitle> 
		<text><![CDATA[Here is the proposed $62 billion budget. The crisis on Wall Street has blasted a $2.7 billion hole. To fill it, you can cut or increase spending or you can raise or lower taxes. Beware of angry cries from officials, groups and citizens.
And, don't forget, spending and revenues must match. It's the law.]]></text> 
		<play_button>Balance the Budget</play_button> 
	</SplashPage> 
	
	<DashboardPage> 
		<expenditures> 
			<title>SPENDING</title> 
			<text><![CDATA[Mayor Michael Bloomberg has already called for two rounds of spending slashes, equal to about 5 percent and 7 percent respectively. But the specifics of those cuts do not exist -- and City Council has already raised objections.
You can start with the spending figures from the revised fiscal year 2009 budget, released in November.]]></text> 
		</expenditures> 
		
		<revenues> 
			<title>REVENUE</title> 
			<text><![CDATA[Politicians and experts have proposed a number of schemes to raise revenue in these tough times. Which, if any, do you like? Warning: Some require approval in Albany.]]></text> 
		</revenues> 
		
		<deficit> 
			<title>DEFICIT</title> 
			<text><![CDATA[(and things could get worse)]]></text> 
		</deficit> 
		
		<compare> 
			<title>COMPARE</title> 
			<text><![CDATA[Done? See how your spending stacks up.]]></text> 
		</compare> 
 
	</DashboardPage> 
	
	<ExpendituresPage> 
		<tip><![CDATA[Move the sliders to cut or increase funding for city programs -- and find out what barriers stand in your way.]]></tip> 
		<source><![CDATA[Spending figures are based on the revised fiscal year 2009 budget, including agency cuts of 2.5 percent. Last year, the mayor proposed to snip another 5 percent, and more recently an additional 7 percent from agencies.]]></source> 
		<numbers>--</numbers> 
		
		<lastyear> 
			<title>SPENDING FOR 2008-2009</title> 
		</lastyear> 
		
		<projected> 
			<title>YOUR PROJECTED EXPENDING</title> 
		</projected> 
		
		<changes> 
			<title>YOUR DEFICIT</title> 
		</changes> 
		
		<pagename>EXPENDINGS</pagename>
 
		<sliderMargin>18</sliderMargin> 
		<sliderMax>9999999999</sliderMax> 
		<sliders> 
			<item><!--aging--> 
				<title>Aging</title> 
				<value>298851000</value> 
				<tip><![CDATA[The projected 2009-2010 fiscal budget for Department for the Aging, which provides services to the city's rapidly growing number of senior citizens, is almost $299 million.]]></tip> 
				<news>none</news> 
				<info><![CDATA[New York City's Department for the Aging funds senior centers throughout the city, meals delivered to about 17,000 elderly people, home care services for some 4,500 frail low-income elderly people, 28 so-called naturally occurring retirement communities providing 45,000 people with services aimed at keeping them out of institutions, as well as support services and other assistance to some 6,000 people who care for elderly New Yorkers.

	

Budget cuts already will eliminate 15 adult social daycare programs intended for people with Alzheimer's, dementia or other disabilities. 

	

><b>Recommended Reading:</b> 
<a href="http://www.gothamgazette.com/article/socialservices/20080908/15/2641">Meeting the Gray Wave</a> (September 2008) and <a href="http://www.gothamgazette.com/article/fea/20080317/202/2465">Aging in a New Era</a> (August 2008)]]></info> 
				<alert></alert> 
			</item> 
			<item><!--children--> 
				<title>Children and Youth</title> 
				<value>3109383000</value> 
				<tip><![CDATA[The "children and youth" budget includes the spending for the city's Administration for Children's Services and its Department of Youth and Community Development.]]></tip> 
				<news></news> 
				<info><![CDATA[The Administration Children's Services has an annual budget of $2.73 billion that it spends investigating allegations of child abuse and neglect, providing services designed to keep thousands of children in their homes and out of foster care, supporting 16,000 children in foster care and group homes and placing children with adoptive families where necessary. In addition, Children's Services provides day care to almost 120,000 eligible children in New York City.

	

In 2006, following the outcry over the beating death of 7-year-old Nixzmary Brown, Bloomberg gave children's services an additional $16 million to hire managers and caseworkers and increase training for current caseworkers. In 2008-2009 Children's Services' budget was increased by $4.9 million to improve children's protection and investigation of abuse. 

	

As young people find it difficult to get summer jobs and other employment, many will look for the city for assistance. The Department of Youth and Community Development administers after-school programs for 78,000 children as well as an internship program that serves 1,300 teens and a range of programs designed to prevent teen pregnancy, keep teens in school and out of all sorts of trouble. The Department of Youth and Community Development budget is $375 million.

	

><b>Recommended Reading:</b> 
<a href="http://www.gothamgazette.com/article/children/20060126/2/1737">Honoring Nixzmary's Memory with a Proper Response</a> (January 2006), <a href="http://www.gothamgazette.com/article/measuringup/20060612/209/1877">Childstat</a> (June 2006), <a href="http://www.gothamgazette.com/article/issueoftheweek/20080804/200/2600">Giving Foster Teens a Place to Call Home </a> (August 2008), <a href="http://www.gothamgazette.com/article/fea/20070904/202/2274">Too Few Jobs for Youth</a> (September 2007)]]></info> 
				<alert><![CDATA[If New Yorkers believe that a child has been injured or killed at the hands of an abusive parent, spending cuts at the Administration for Children's Services could quickly produce outrage. [CAN WE INCLUCE A GRAPHIC HERE? A NIXMARY HEADLINE, MAYBE?)]]></alert> 
			</item> 
			<item><!--corrections--> 
				<title>Corrections</title> 
				<value>1070865000</value> 
				<tip><![CDATA[Despite a drop in crime, New York City still spends a bit more than $1 billion a year on running its local prisons and supervising people who have recently been released.

				]]></tip> 
				<news>The lion's share of the city corrections budget goes to the Department of Correction, but this figure also includes the Board of Correction and the Department of Probation.</news> 
				<info><![CDATA[The Department of Correction, which has a $985.4 million budget, oversees custody of anyone awaiting trial or sentencing as well as convicts sentenced to serve not more than a year. The department is responsible for an inmate population that averages 14,000 prisoners every day, and runs initiatives that provide educational opportunities to young people detained on Riker's Island or who were recently released from custody. The Department also evaluates alternatives to incarceration, including one program for people arrested for certain nonviolent offenses.

The number of people detained in city jails has gone down by a daily average of about 3,500 since 1998. Some experts fear a failing economy could lead to an increase in crime, which would, in turn, increase costs for the correction department.

The Board of Correction, with a budget of $934,000, is responsible for ensuring that city jails meet standards for incarcerating inmates.

The Department of Probation has an $85 million budget, which it spends on pre-sentencing interviews with people convicted of crimes and supervision of former prisoners released prior to the end of their sentences. Individuals who are on probation are supposed to find work, attend school and otherwise become part of their communities, and the Probation department is responsible for supervising them as they do so. 

><b>Recommended Reading:</b> 
<a href="http://www.gothamgazette.com/article/issueoftheweek/20080211/200/2427">Barred Medicine: Health Care on Riker's Island</a> (February 2008), <a href="http://www.gothamgazette.com/article/crime/20080603/200/2545">Can New York Breaks Its Incarceration Habit?</a> (June 2008)]]></info> 
				<alert></alert> 
			</item> 
			<item><!--education--> 
				<title>Education</title> 
				<value>18271607000</value> 
				<tip><![CDATA[By far, the largest recipient of city funds, the Department of Education has a budget of $17.6 billion. Here, we also include the City University of New York's $695 million.]]></tip> 
				<news>"Dec 16, 2008: Governor Paterson's budget proposes to cut X from education funds that the city counts on. If we don't want to cut programs or increase class sizes, New York City will have to make up the difference."</news> 
				<info><![CDATA[By far, the largest recipient of city funds, the Department of Education has an operating budget of $17.6 billion, of which more than $8 billion comes from the state. All that local, state and federal money goes to educate about 1.1 million public school students, including 109,000 children who require full-time special needs programs. The department employs about 113,000 full-time teachers and other "pedagogical' staff, operates more than 1,400 schools and provides a range of additional support services to city students, including transportation and meals.

New York City's public school system has undergone substantial change and reorganization over the past seven years, and its funding increased a total of 48 percent from 2002 to 2009. Education advocates have called for further increases, particularly in state funding, noting that the city still lags behind suburban school districts. With Gov. David Paterson calling instead for a cut in aid to the city's schools, advocates will resist reductions to city spending on schools.

City University of New York is the largest municipal university system in the country. CUNY's $695 million budget funds 11 four-year universities, six community colleges, a law school, a journalism school, the Graduate Center and a variety of graduate and professional schools. CUNY's 463,000 students are divided almost evenly between students in degree programs and students not in degree programs. 

City colleges have played a key role in the advancement of generations of immigrants, but fell on hard times following the 1970s fiscal crisis. They began to gain increased prestige in the last few years with more hiring, higher admissions standards and the institution of honors programs. Any effort to cut spending could undermine these efforts. In addition, with Paterson proposing to increase tuition at CUNY, city officials may face pressure to ease that pain by expanding student aid.

><b>Recommended Reading:</b> 
<a href="http://www.gothamgazette.com/article/education/20070123/6/2084">Reorganizing the Schools – Again</a> (January 2007), <a href="http://www.gothamgazette.com/article/education/20061127/6/2044">The Last Word in School Funding</a> (November 2006), <a href="http://www.gothamgazette.com/article/education/20080528/6/2537">Anger and Accusations Greet Budget Cuts</a> (May 2008), <a href="http://www.gothamgazette.com/article/issueoftheweek/20071029/200/2330">College Boom</a> (October 2007)]]></info> 
				<alert><![CDATA[City education advocates are vocal and organized and include the politically powerful teacher's union. They will oppose classroom cuts! And many on City Council will listen.  

To make matter trickier, school funding can be a minefield: Any call for cuts in classes will produce new scrutiny of -- and outrage over -- many of Bloomberg's prized education initiatives, particularly the $80 million ARIS supercomputer and its standardized testing program.]]></alert> 
			</item> 
			<item><!--fire--> 
				<title>Fire</title> 
				<value>1569331000</value> 
				<tip><![CDATA[The Fire Department's budget includes money to run firehouses as well as to operate Emergency Medical Services and fund fire prevention programs and inspections.]]></tip> 
				<news></news> 
				<info><![CDATA[The Fire Department has an annual operating budget of $1.6 billion to run about 330 fire companies. The department is called to put out some 50,000 fires every year in addition to responding to other emergencies, providing medical care and ambulance services through Emergency Medical Services. The Fire Department enforces the fire code and educates New Yorkers about preventing fires. 

The Fire Department closed six fire companies in the financial crunch following the Sept. 11, 2001 attacks. This prompted concern about increased response times, though recent studies show that the "bravest" reach the average structural fire four minutes and nine seconds after dispatchers receive the call.

><b>Recommended Reading:</b> 
<a href="http://www.gothamgazette.com/iotw/firedepartment/">The Fire Department</a>, <a href="http://www.gothamgazette.com/article/issueoftheweek/20030811/200/486">Closing Firehouses</a> (August 2003)]]></info> 
				<alert><![CDATA[

CAN WE USE A FIREHOUSE PHOTO? OR A BURNING BUILDING? Almost any community will fight hard if its see its fire company threatened -- as residents feel their lives hang in the balance. Just ask former Mayor David Dinkins: He closed a firehouse only to see two men die in a blaze in the community only days later. The tragedy emerged as an issue in the next mayoral campaign. (Dinkins lost.)]]></alert> 
			</item> 
			<item><!--health--> 
				<title>Health and Public Hospitals</title> 
				<value>1898582000</value> 
				<tip><![CDATA[City spending on public health is split between the Department of Health and Mental Hygiene, which has run high-profile public health campaigns, and the Health and Hospitals Corp.]]></tip> 
				<news></news> 
				<info><![CDATA[The Department of Health and Mental Hygiene has a budget of $1.7 billion which funds health services in public schools; public health campaigns on such issues as stopping smoking, substance abuse and prevention of HIV/AIDS; restaurant inspections; mental health services for 450,000 New Yorkers annually; and various programs to make health care available to all New Yorkers; and analysis of information on outbreaks of disease and health data. 

With a mayor who has a particular interest in health, the department has been in the forefront of many of Bloomberg's key initiatives including the efforts to encourage New Yorkers to eat healthier foods and the controversial smoking ban, generally credited with having sharply reduced smoking in the city. The department's budget has been on the rise in recent years to support these initiatives, increasing more than 17 percent from 2007 to 2008.

Health and Hospitals is a $5.4 billion corporation, but only $200 million of that comes from city coffers. The Health and Hospitals Corp. serves 1.3 million New Yorkers and operates 11 acute care hospitals, four skilled nursing facilities, six large diagnostic and treatment centers and more than 80 community based clinics. The corporation has its own deficit to grapple with -- city funds represent only a small part of the picture.

><b>Recommended Reading:</b> 
<a href="http://www.gothamgazette.com/article/issueoftheweek/20040809/200/1082"> The Urban Health Challenge</a> (August 2004), <a href="http://www.gothamgazette.com/article/health/20040514/9/979"> Smokers Quitting</a> (May 2004), <a href="http://www.gothamgazette.com/article/issueoftheweek/20080303/200/2456/">Fighting the Obesity Epidemic</a> (March 2008), <a href="http://www.gothamgazette.com/article/health/20071018/9/2324/">Grading the City's Public Hospitals</a> (October 2007)		]]></info> 
				<alert></alert> 
			</item> 
			<item><!--libraries--> 
				<title>Libraries and Culture</title> 
				<value>454194000</value> 
				<tip><![CDATA[New York City spends $303 million a year to fund the three public library systems for the five boroughs, and $151 million on museums and other cultural institutions.]]></tip> 
				<news></news> 
				<info><![CDATA[New York City is home to three separate public library systems. The New York Public Library operates four research libraries and 85 branches in Manhattan, the Bronx and Staten Island. Brooklyn Public Library has a single central library, a business library and 58 branches. Queens Library runs a central library and 61 local branches.

Budget cuts have played havoc with library hours since the fiscal crisis of the 1970s. As late as the 1990s, some libraries were open just 14 hours a week. Hours increased but immediately after Sept. 11, 2001, they were drastically cut again. It wasn't until 2007 that City Council approved funds to ensure all libraries would be open six days a week.

The Department of Cultural Affairs supports operations at 34 city-owned cultural institutions, including the Metropolitan Museum of Art, El Museo de Barrio and Brooklyn Academy of Music. Grants and other services support 850 performance groups, cultural organizations and independently owned museums.

><b>Recommended Reading:</b> 
<a href="http://www.gothamgazette.com/iotw/library/">The New Libraries</a> (April 2001), <a href="http://www.gothamgazette.com/article/arts/20070131/1/2091">Arts Funding Transformed</a> (January 2007), <a href="http://www.gothamgazette.com/article/arts/20081217/1/2782">Cultural Groups Wonder Just How Bad Things Will Get</a> (December 2008)]]></info> 
				<alert></alert> 
			</item> 
			<item><!--parks--> 
				<title>Parks and Recreation</title> 
				<value>359136000</value> 
				<tip><![CDATA[The Department of Parks and Recreation manages nearly 30,000 acres of city parks, including open spaces, playgrounds, tennis courts, nature centers and beaches. ]]></tip> 
				<news></news> 
				<info><![CDATA[Public parks account for 14 percent of New York City's landmass. The Department of Parks and Recreation has a $359 million budget its uses to manages 800 individual properties that, combined, make up 29,000 acres of open space. Parks operates recreational facilities including 1,000 playgrounds, 54 swimming pools and 14 miles of beach, cares for 600,00 trees on city streets, and maintains some 1,200 monuments.

The Bloomberg administration has launched a number of new parks projects, but to fund them the city has relied increasingly on private sources of money, such as corporate and individual donations, events and private use of the parks, all of which could prove vulnerable in a recession.

><b>Recommended Reading:</b> 
<a href="http://www.gothamgazette.com/article/issueoftheweek/20040315/200/910">The Parks Renaissance</a> (March 2004), <a href="http://www.gothamgazette.com/article/issueoftheweek/20060807/200/1927">Funding the Parks Boom</a> (August 2006), <a href="http://www.gothamgazette.com/article/fea/20070129/202/2088">Private Partnerships for Public Parks</a> (January 2007) ]]></info> 
				<alert></alert> 
			</item> 
			<item><!--police--> 
				<title>Police</title> 
				<value>4427878000</value> 
				<tip><![CDATA[The Police Department has reduced some of its civilian positions and, under the adjustments to the 2009 budget, will scale back the number of new recruits for 2009.]]></tip> 
				<news></news> 
				<info><![CDATA[The New York City Police Department has a $4.4 billion budget to spend patrolling city streets, the transit system and schools, investigating crimes, responding to emergency calls and pursuing anti-terrorism measures. With 94 percent of the police budget going for personnel the department says the only way to save meaningful amount of money is to reduce officers. Crime continued to fall throughout the first years of 21st century, with the city reporting, that in 2007, crime had declined 6 percent from the previous year and dropped by 26 percent from 2001. This, the administration likes to say, has made New York "the safest big city America." However the trend shows signs of abating and even reversing, with murders up by about 6 percent this year.

The city spends $11 million a year on the Civilian Complaint Review Board to investigate alleged cases of police misconduct.

><b>Recommended Reading:</b> <a href="http://www.gothamgazette.com/article/demographics/20040517/5/982">Why Is There a Plunge in Crime?</a> (May 2004), <a href="http://www.gothamgazette.com/article/issueoftheweek/20050228/200/1335">The Crime Rate: How Low Can It Go?</a> (February 2005), <a href="http://www.gothamgazette.com/article/fea/20071217/202/2382">Who's Stopped? Who's Frisked?</a> (December 2007)]]></info> 
				<alert><![CDATA[Beware the ghost of the 1980s and early 1990s. Police unions and other warn cuts in the police force could bring back the days when more than 2,000 people in the city lost their lives to violent crime every year.]]></alert> 
			</item> 
			<item><!--sanitation--> 
				<title>Sanitation</title> 
				<value>1281762000</value> 
				<tip><![CDATA[Disposing of the garbage from all city's households and keeping its streets clean and snow-free costs $1.3 billion a year -- and that figure is likely to increase.]]></tip> 
				<news></news> 
				<info><![CDATA[The Department of Sanitation's budget is $1.3 billion. With this money, Sanitation collects residential garbage from curbsides throughout the city, transporting and disposing of 11,700 tons of waste a day. The department also collects recyclables and arranges for them to be recycled.

As the city has found it increasingly difficult to find places to dispose of its garbage, the cost of disposal has risen. While the drop in energy costs may offer the department, with its many trucks and high shipping costs, a respite that could change if gas prices soar again.

><b>Recommended Games and Reading:</b> 
<a href="http://www.gothamgazette.com/article/gamesandquizzes/20071113/201/2343">The Garbage Glut</a> (November 2007) <a href="http://www.gothamgazette.com/games/garbage.php">Gotham Gazette's Garbage Game</a> (November 2007)]]></info> 
				<alert><![CDATA[Dirty streets and piles of moldering refuse are ugly, unhealthy and a trademark of an ailing city. The mayor has said we won't go back to the bad old days of dirty streets.]]></alert> 
			</item> 
			<item><!--social services--> 
				<title>Social and Homeless Services</title> 
				<value>9314713000</value> 
				<tip><![CDATA[This combines the departments of Homeless Services and Social Services, which provide assistance to New Yorkers in need. Social Services accounts for the lion's share of this.]]></tip> 
				<news></news> 
				<info><![CDATA[The Department of Social Services has a budget of $8.5 billion that it spends to assist New Yorkers in need. Social Services administers support services, cash assistance and other programs, provides local management of the federal Food Stamp program which provides benefits to more than 798,000 New Yorkers, operates specialized job centers, provides service to more than 30,000 people with AIDS or advanced HIV, operates an emergency shelter program for victims of domestic violence, works to collect child support payments from non-custodial parents, enrolls and certifies people in the Medicaid health insurance program for low-income people. 

The number of New Yorkers on public assistance has dropped fairly steadily since 2002. At the same time, though, the number of people receiving Food Stamps has grown. Charities in the city have already reported an increase in demand for their services, particularly food, since the onset of the recession.

The Department of Homeless Services has a $782 million budget with which to operate shelters for people without any other place to stay, run drop-in centers, help New Yorkers move into supportive or transitional housing and work to prevent individuals and families from becoming homeless and ending up in the shelter system.

Bloomberg's efforts to sharply reduce homelessness have fallen far short of his goals. The situation has proved particularly intractable for homeless families, whose numbers have increased since 2005. 

><b>Recommended Reading:</b> 
<a href="http://www.gothamgazette.com/article/issueoftheweek/20060925/200/1981">Fighting Poverty</a> (September 2006), <a href="http://www.gothamgazette.com/article/20060619/200/1887">Fighting Poverty and a Decade of Welfare Reform</a> (September 2006), <a href="http://www.gothamgazette.com/slideshows/1208nycharities/">Hard-Times Holiday</a> (December 2008), <a href="http://www.gothamgazette.com/article/issueoftheweek/20080922/200/2655">The Long Fight to End Homelessness</a> (September 2008)]]></info> 
				<alert></alert> 
			</item> 
			<item><!--transportation--> 
				<title>Transportation</title> 
				<value>789968000</value> 
				<tip><![CDATA[The Department of Transportation maintains 5,700 miles of streets, complete with streetlights and traffic signals, as well as the bridges and tunnels that link the five boroughs.]]></tip> 
				<news></news> 
				<info><![CDATA[The Department of Transportation has $790 million to spend maintaining 88 bridges and tunnels in the five boroughs as well as 5,700 miles of streets and all the streetlights, traffic lights and traffic signs that illuminate them. The department also operates ferry service between Manhattan and Staten Island and runs programs designed to encourage cycling in the city. 

Once known as the Traffic Department, the Department of Transportation has recently begun to morph from an agency primarily concerned with keeping cars and trucks moving through city streets to one that promotes alternatives to driving. It has tried to establish safer lanes and paths for cycling, expanded sidewalks and set some street space aside for walking (and sometimes even sitting). The Department of Transportation is independent from the Metropolitan Transportation Authority or MTA, which operates our public transportation system with a combination of city state and federal funding.

><b>Recommended Reading:</b> 
<a href="http://www.gothamgazette.com/article/environment/20080527/210/2534">A Smoother Ride for Cycling in the City</a> (May 2008), <a href="http://www.gothamgazette.com/article/parks/20071130/210/2361">Creating People Friendly Streets</a> (November 2007), <a href="http://www.gothamgazette.com/article/transportation/20070213/16/2104">Sustainable Transportation for 2030</a> (February 2007)]]></info> 
				<alert></alert> 
			</item> 
			<item><!--urban environment--> 
				<title>Urban Environment</title> 
				<value>1064261000</value> 
				<tip><![CDATA[The Department of Environmental Protection and the Department of City Planning share responsibility for the urban environment, including clean water and allotting the use of space.]]></tip> 
				<news></news> 
				<info><![CDATA[The Department of Environmental Protection has a $1 billion budget with which to provide the city with 1.3 billion gallons of drinking water a day, collecting that water upstate and delivering it to city faucets. The Department also treats an average of 1.3 billion gallons of sewage everyday that it does not rain (and when it rains, they have bigger problems), enforces air and water quality regulations, noise rules and responds to any emergency involving hazardous materials.

New York City's tap water has an international reputation for taste and quality, but maintaining that reputation requires constant vigilance. New York's sewers, are easily overwhelmed by heavy rainfall and often send raw sewage spilling into surrounding waterways.

The Department of City Planning has a budget of $31 million. It is responsible for reviewing zoning and other land use plans and environmental reviews of changes to zoning. The department also provides guidance on the long term planning and development of the city technical assistance and data, including demographic information, related to planning.

The Bloomberg administration has undertaken to rezone an unprecedented number of city neighborhoods and launched a number of major development projects. Responsibility for these changes has fallen to the planning department, which drafts proposals, compiles reports and holds hearings on often controversial plans.

><b>Recommended Reading:</b> 
<a href="http://www.gothamgazette.com/article/environment/20030217/7/286">Water</a> (February 2003), <a href="http://www.gothamgazette.com/article/parks/20040723/14/1064">The Filtration Plant in Van Cortland Park</a> (July 2004), <a href="http://www.gothamgazette.com/article/issueoftheweek/20031020/200/569">The Sewer System</a> (October 2003), <a href="http://www.gothamgazette.com/article/issueoftheweek/20070813/200/2258">Crumbling Systems</a> (August 2007)]]></info> 
				<alert></alert> 
			</item> 
			<item> 
				<title>All other departments</title> 
				<value>10133490000</value> 
				<tip>The city budget also includes HOW MANY administrative offices and departments whose budgets combine to over $10 billion.</tip> 
				<news>text</news> 
				<info>Text TK</info> 
				<alert></alert> 
			</item> 
			<item><!--uncontrollable--> 
				<title>"Uncontrollables"</title> 
				<value>8002820000</value> 
				<tip><![CDATA[This mayor and his predecessors have argued that much of the budget is beyond their control: Pensions and debt service combined account for 13 percent of the city's budget. ]]></tip> 
				<news></news> 
				<info><![CDATA[Payments to the city's pension funds employees was estimated to cost $6.3 billion this fiscal year. And it is projected to go up -- to $6.9 billion in 2010 and $7.3 billion in 2011. Meanwhile the pension funds, recently valued at $112 billion, have seen their value collapse because of the turmoil on Wall Street. Experts, though see little cause for panic -- if the markets rebound.

Is this out of our control? The city and state must deliver on what they have promised. But government could reduce benefits for future workers. A test may come as Gov. David Paterson seeks to roll back pension benefits for new public employees in New York. Pensions are part of collective bargaining agreements with public employee unions.

Meanwhile, some watchdog groups argue that public employees should have retirement savings accounts, with an employer contribution, such as $401-K instead of getting old-fashioned fixed pensions -- a tough sell when so any Americans have seen their retirement accounts sharply diminish in value. And even if the city changes to 401-Ks, it won't help with our present pension burden.

New York City borrows money to fund construction of schools, roads, subway stations and other facilities. Debt service, or interest payments on that money borrowed, will cost the government $1.7 billion this year. It's estimated to fall to $1.1 billion in 2010 because the Bloomberg administration paid almost $2 billion in debt early. The savings won't last, though: New York City's debt service obligations are projected at $4.5 billion in 2011 and will reach $6.5 billion in 2012.

What can the city do about debt service costs? For the immediate future, not much. The administration has already prepaid some debt and has scaled back capital projects, many of which are financed by borrowing. 

Experts do see ways for greater savings in the future: New York City could accumulate less debt by paying for more projects out of operating expenses instead of borrowed funds, and by spending construction dollars more carefully.

><b>Recommended Reading:</b> 
<a href="http://www.gothamgazette.com/article/issueoftheweek/20050530/200/1430">Unfunded Mandates and 'Uncontrollables'</a> (May 2005) <a href="http://www.gothamgazette.com/article/finance/20050208/8/131">State Debt + Federal Debt = City Budget Trouble</a> (February 2005)]]></info> 
				<alert></alert> 
			</item> 
<!--			<item>
				<title>Default</title>
				<value>0</value>
				<tip>text</tip>
				<news>text</news>
				<info>text</info>
				<alert>text</alert>
			</item>--> 
		</sliders> 
		
	</ExpendituresPage> 
	
	<RevenuesPage> 
		
		<lastyear> 
			<title>INCOME FOR 2008-2009</title> 
		</lastyear> 
		
		<projected> 
			<title>YOUR PROJECTION</title> 
		</projected> 
		
		<changes> 
			<title>YOUR DEFICIT</title> 
		</changes>
		
		<pagename>REVENUES</pagename>
		
		<tip><![CDATA[Choose from a menu of options to bring more money into city coffers. Click on any option for more information.]]></tip> 
		<source><![CDATA[coming]]></source> 
		
		<box><![CDATA[With the economy in turmoil, revenue projections are dicey at best. In his November projections, Mayor Michael Bloomberg forecast slightly over $60 billion in city revenues for the 2010 fiscal year. A decline in wages, a loss of 147,000 private sector jobs and a drop in home sales were all forecasted. The administration then predicted Wall Street would once again become profitable at the end of 2009. Is this overly

optimistic? For now, take his number, subtract reductions in state aid, and try to cover all of the city's costs.]]></box> 
		
		<cityTitle>Changes the City Can Make</cityTitle> 
		<stateTitle>Changes that Require State Approval</stateTitle> 
		<sliderMargin>20</sliderMargin> 
		
		<baseIncome>1000000000</baseIncome>
		
		<city> 
			<item><!--clothing--> 
				<value>436000000</value> 
				<title><![CDATA[Restore the sales tax on clothing]]></title> 
				<!-- gov: city --> 
				<!--type: check off--> 
				<news></news> 
				<check>0</check> 
				<tip><![CDATA[The city removed the 4 percent sales tax on all clothing in 2007 but some say that is a luxury it can no longer afford. The state taxes apparel costing $110 or more.]]></tip> 
				<info><![CDATA[Restore the Sales Tax on Clothing: $436 million

Sales and use taxes are expected to account for $4.7 billion of city revenues this fiscal year. In light of the recession, the city anticipates that this will drop to $4.5 billion next year. Boosting the tax in some way might make up for some of the shortfall.

One plan would restore the 4 percent city sales tax on clothing. The state places a sales tax on any item of clothing costing $110 or more. In September 2007, the city eliminated the tax on any piece of clothing -- regardless of cost.

Restoring the tax on all clothing would bring in an anticipated $436 million next year. Taxing only items of clothing costing $110 or more would generate an estimated $119 million in revenue.

Gov. Paterson wants the state to reinstate the tax on clothing under $110. Adding in the city tax could be seen as too much of a burden, particularly on low-income families. A tax on higher end items might be more palatable, although critics have always said that comparatively higher sales tax here could spur New Yorkers to buy less or try to avoid sales taxes by shopping outside the city.

><b>Recommended reading:</b> <a href="http://www.gothamgazette.com/article/finance/20070928/8/2301">Reviewing Federal and City Tax Cuts</a> (September 2007)
					]]></info> 
			</item> 
			<item><!--salestax--> 
				<value>292000000</value> 
				<title><![CDATA[Increase the sales tax by 0.25 percent]]></title> 
				<!-- gov: city --> 
				<news></news> 
				<check>1</check> 
				<tip><![CDATA[Even if New York City increased its local sales tax by one quarter of a percentage point, shoppers would still pay less of a tax in Manhattan than they do in Utica.]]></tip> 
				<info><![CDATA[Increase the Sales Tax by 0.25 Percent

Sales and use taxes are expected to account for $4.7 billion in city revenues this fiscal year. In light of the recession, the city anticipates that this will drop to $4.5 billion next year. Boosting the tax in some way might make up for at least some of the shortfall.

One plan would increase the city's sales by .25 percent, bringing the combined state and local charge on all taxable goods to 8.625 percent. That is still less than the rate in Utica: 8.75 percent.

For better or worse, the hike would leave the tax structure in its current form, just adding a modest increase. Coming on top of other tax increases and proposed new taxes though, citizens might find it difficult to accept.

><b>Recommended reading:</b> <a href="http://www.gothamgazette.com/article/finance/20081128/8/2769">The Mayor's Budget-Cutting Strategy</a> (November 2008)
					]]></info> 
				<alert><![CDATA[Are you willing to be the Grinch who stole shopping?

City merchants were hit by a weak holiday season. Things promise to be grim with fewer Wall Street types able to afford four-digit designer suits. Is this really the time for government to extract another penalty on spending money?]]></alert> 
			</item> 
			<item><!--preservehoteltax--> 
				<value>8000000</value> 
				<title><![CDATA[Preserve the 0.875 percent increase in the hotel tax]]></title> 
				<!-- gov: city --> 
				<news></news> 
				<check>0</check> 
				<tip><![CDATA[The increase in the hotel tax enacted by City Council in November 2008 added $2.62 a night to the tab for an average -- though still pricey -- New York City hotel room.]]></tip> 
				<info><![CDATA[Preserve the Hotel Tax Hike: $80 million

In late December, the City Council voted to increase the city's hotel tax from 5 percent to 5.875 percent, adding $2.62 to the price of an average $300 room. Keeping the extra charge would add $80 million this year.

Proponents of the tax said everyone -- including visitors -- should have to bear some of the burden of the city's hard times. Tourists depend on city services, supporters argue, including police and fire protection. They also said the increase was hardly enough to keep someone from visiting New York.

But hotel and other tourism officials said the extra fee could deter travel and be particularly damaging to the convention business. 

During the past several years, tourism, particularly from overseas, has been a booming part of the city economy.

><b>Recommended reading:</b> <a href="http://www.gothamgazette.com/article/searchlight/20081209/203/2779">Tax Bills on the Floor</a> (December 2008), <a href="http://www.gothamgazette.com/article/issueoftheweek/20040531/200/993">Tourism and Jobs</a> (May 2004), <a href="http://www.gothamgazette.com/article/issueoftheweek/20060626/200/1893">New York City Tourism</a> (June 2008)
					]]></info> 
			</item> 
			<item><!--propertyhike--> 
				<value>5760000</value> 
				<title><![CDATA[Raise the property tax another 7 percent]]></title> 
				<!-- gov: city --> 
				<news></news> 
				<check>1</check> 
				<tip><![CDATA[In 2002 and 2003, the city raised property taxes by 18.5 percent to get through tough times after Sept. 11, 2001. Will the mayor and City Council turn to such increases again?]]></tip> 
				<info><![CDATA[Property Tax Hike: $576 million

The city gets about $14 billion a year from the property tax. In November, the mayor and the City Council agreed to increase the property tax by 7 percent. Another similar hike next year would bring in about $576 million.

The November action was couched as rescinding a decrease. This would be an increase -- and would be viewed as such. It would cost the average city homeowner about $240 a year. 

><b>Recommended reading:</b> <a href="http://www.gothamgazette.com/article/finance/20080208/8/2426">Tax Breaks -- Who Wins and Who Loses?</a> (February 2008), <a href="http://www.gothamgazette.com/article/searchlight/20081218/203/2784">Council Passes Budget Cuts</a> (December 2008)
					]]></info> 
				<alert><![CDATA[2009 is an election year. Politicians hate to raise taxes -- but they really, really hate to raise taxes in an election year. And City Council members facing re-election have already ticked off some of their constituents by opting to extend term limits. Will they risk making voters even madder?]]></alert> 
			</item> 
		</city> 
		<state> 
			<item><!--restore_education--> 
				<title><![CDATA[Restore proposed cuts in state education funding]]></title> 
				<value>20600000</value> 
				<!-- gov: state --> 
				<news></news> 
				<check>1</check> 
				<tip><![CDATA[The fight over state aid to city schools goes back decades, if not longer, and the governor's plan to cut the funding instead of increasing it has attracted intense opposition.]]></tip> 
				<info><![CDATA[Restore Proposed State Cuts in Education Aid: $206 million

This fiscal year, the city Department of Education received about $8.5 billion of its $17.6 billion budget from the state. State aid to city schools has been set to continue to increase as a result of settlement in the long running lawsuit over state financing of the New York City public schools.

But in his proposed budget presented in December, Gov. David Paterson called not just for a slowing of the increase but an actual $206 million cut in aid to city schools -- part of a $700 million reduction in education aid statewide.

In the coming months, as they negotiate the state budget, legislators could win a restoration of the aid. But with the state facing a $15 billion deficit, they need to cut somewhere, raise lots of taxes -- or, more likely, both.

><b>Recommended reading:</b> <a href="http://gothamgazette.com/article/education/20061127/6/2044">The Last Word in School Funding</a> (November 2006) ]]></info> 
			</item> 
			<item><!--restore_local_aid--> 
				<title><![CDATA[Restore proposed cuts in the state's local aid to the city]]></title> 
				<value>24600000</value> 
				<!-- gov: state --> 
				<news></news> 
				<check>0</check> 
				<tip><![CDATA[Gov, David Paterson wants to cut general municipal aid to New York City while preserving assistance to other cities, which, he said, do not have as many other sources of revenue.]]></tip> 
				<info><![CDATA[Restore Cut in General State Aid to the City: $246 million

Municipal aid from the state to New York City was set to reach $328 million next year. Instead, Gov. David Paterson wants to cut the aid, now at $246 million, entirely. He plans to continue aid to other cities but thinks New York "has a range of local revenue sources" to replace its pot of state money. 

Mayor Michael Bloomberg, though, said the city already pays more than its fair share, accounting for roughly 40 percent of the state's population but paying 50 percent of its taxes.

					

					]]></info> 
				<alert><![CDATA[Can you really argue New York City is in worst shape than Buffalo?]]></alert> 
			</item> 
			<item><!--toll_east_river--> 
				<title><![CDATA[Toll the East River Bridges ]]></title> 
				<value>830000000</value> 
				<!-- gov: state --> 
				<news></news> 
				<check>0</check> 
				<tip><![CDATA[For 80 years, various officials have tried to charge tolls on the East River bridges, but the crossings have remained free. Now some want charges on the Harlem River bridges as well.]]></tip> 
				<info><![CDATA[Toll the Bridges: $830 million

The idea keeps popping up but never gets beyond talk. Now the Ravitch Commission, formed to review the Metropolitan Transportation Authority's bleak finances, would end the free ride across the East River and Harlem River. It calls for tolls on the four free East River crossings -- the 59th Street, Williamsburg, Manhattan and Brooklyn bridges -- equivalent to the amount now charged to go over other East River crossings. The fee to drive across the nine Harlem River Bridges would be equal to a subway ride.

Various transit advocates and city officials have been seeking tolls on the bridges at least since the 1930s -- always in vain. Mayor Michael Bloomberg floated the idea during the financial crunch after the Sept. 11, 2001 attacks. In 2007, Bloomberg took a similar, slightly different tact, proposing to charge people to drive into Manhattan (which, of course, requires going across some bridge or tunnel). At the time, some proposed tolling the bridges as a simple alternative. In the end, neither was approved.

Even if the legislature does agree to the tolls -- a heavy lift at best -- the money is by no means certain to go to the city's coffers. The Ravitch Commission wants to set it aside for mass transit. 

><b>Recommended reading:</b> <a href="http://www.gothamgazette.com/article/transportation/20031015/16/559">East River Bridge Toll</a> (October 2003), <a href="http://www.gothamgazette.com/article/fea/20080107/202/2393">A Simpler Alternative to Congestion Pricing</a> (January 2008), <a href="http://www.gothamgazette.com/article/transportation/20081215/16/2781">Paying for Transit: Fares or Fees? Tolls or Taxes?</a> (December 2008)
					]]></info> 
				<alert><![CDATA[Are you sure you can handle being branded an "enemy of the working class" by Brooklyn Borough President Marty Markowitz?]]></alert> 
			</item> 
			<item><!--restore_commuter--> 
				<title><![CDATA[Restore the commuter tax ]]></title> 
				<value>75500000</value> 
				<!-- gov: state --> 
				<news></news> 
				<check>0</check> 
				<tip><![CDATA[The commuter tax died in 1999, the victim of some Byzantine political maneuvering in Albany. Now it cannot be restored without the approval of the state government.]]></tip> 
				<info><![CDATA[Restore the Commuter Tax: $755 million

From 1971 until 1999, commuters paid a 0.45 percent tax on their salaries earned in the city and a 0.65 percent payment on self-employment income. The tax was then eliminated, as part of an unsuccessful maneuver by Democrats, including many representing the city, to win a contested state Assembly seat.

Not surprisingly, a lot of city politicians would like to see the commuter tax reinstated. Unfortunately, doing so requires the approval of the state legislature, and members of the State Senate and Assembly representing the suburbs are unlikely to support a tax on their constituents.

><b>Recommended reading:</b> <a href="http://www.gothamgazette.com/commentary/134.pasanen.shtml">Bringing Back the Commuter Tax</a> (August 2002), <a href="http://www.gothamgazette.com/commentary/134.mcmahon.shtml">The Tax Whose Times Has Gone</a> (August 2002)
					]]></info> 
			</item> 
			<item><!--expand_bottlebill--> 
				<title><![CDATA[Expand and change the bottle bill]]></title> 
				<value>55000000</value> 
				<!-- gov: state --> 
				<news></news> 
				<check>0</check> 
				<tip><![CDATA[The bottle bill dates back to a time before sports drinks and bottled water became popular. Bringing it up to date, advocates say, would bring in money and reduce litter.]]></tip> 
				<info><![CDATA[Bottle Bill Changes: $55 million

Since 1992, New York State has required a 5-cent deposit on containers for many beverages including beer, soda and wine coolers. Customers pay a 5-cent deposit on the drink, which is refunded when they return the cans or bottles. Stores, in turn, receive 5 cents from the distributors when they give them back the containers. Distributors get to keep the money for any containers that are not returned.

Now, environmentalists and others are proposing expanding and changing parts of the law to further reduce waste and generate revenue. For one, they would like the bottle bill to cover more beverages, such as prepared iced tea, sports drinks and bottled water (only mineral water is currently included).

Another measure would no longer allow distributors to keep unredeemed deposits, instead requiring the money to be turned over to the local government. 

In addition to generating revenue, advocates say, these measures could reduce litter. Opponents might see them as putting a further burden on small stores, such as delis and bodegas, by requiring them to collect more containers. And distributors, of course, would not want to lose the unredeemed deposits, money they may well feel they deserve for dealing with the returned containers and the deposit system.

><b>Recommended reading:</b> <a href="http://www.gothamgazette.com/environment/jul.02.shtml">Four Environmental Issues that Albany Could Solve</a> (July 2002)
					]]></info> 
			</item> 
			<item><!--incometax_7--> 
				<title><![CDATA[Increase the city personal income tax by 7.5 percent]]></title> 
				<value>585000000</value> 
				<!-- gov: state --> 
				<news></news> 
				<check>0</check> 
				<tip><![CDATA[The income tax is New York City's second largest source of revenue after the property tax, bringing in abut 22 percent of the city's income in fiscal year 2008. ]]></tip> 
				<info><![CDATA[Raise the Income Tax by 7.5 Percent: $585 million

The city personal income tax was estimated to bring in about $7.2 billion this fiscal year. With fewer big salaries on Wall Street and job losses, the city now anticipates that amount will decline to $6.5 billion in fiscal year 2010 and $6.3 billion in 2011. Increasing the tax rate could compensate for some of that decline.

Taxpayers with taxable incomes of $50,000 to $75,000 would see their city income tax go up $116 a year under this proposal. Those making between $75,000 and $90,000 would have a $178 hike.

A tax hike is always a hard sell and could prove particularly difficult at a time when many New Yorkers are seeing their incomes drop and facing an array of increased and new state taxes, as well as higher property tax and transit fees.

><b>Recommended reading:</b> <a href="http://www.gothamgazette.com/article/finance/20070928/8/2301">Reviewing Federal and City Tax Cuts</a> (September 2007), <a href="http://www.gothamgazette.com/article/finance/20081128/8/2769">The Mayor's Budget Cutting Strategy</a> (November 2008)
					]]></info> 
			</item> 
			<item><!--incometax_15--> 
				<title><![CDATA[Increase the personal income tax by 15 percent]]></title> 
				<value>1200000000</value> 
				<!-- gov: state --> 
				<news></news> 
				<check>0</check> 
				<tip><![CDATA[Any increase in the city's personal income tax would require the approval of the state government, which could also be considering changes in the state income tax.]]></tip> 
				<info><![CDATA[Raise the Income Tax by 15 Percent 

The city personal income tax was estimated to bring in about $7.2 billion this fiscal year. With fewer big salaries on Wall Street and job losses, the city now anticipates that amount will decline to $6.5 billion in fiscal year 2010 and $6.3 billion in 2011. Increasing the tax rate could compensate for some of that decline.

Taxpayers with taxable incomes of $50,000 to $75,000 would see their city income tax go up $233 a year under this proposal. Those making between $75,000 and $90,000 would have a $356 hike.

A tax hike is always a hard sell and could prove particularly difficult at a time when many New Yorkers are seeing their incomes drop and facing an array of increased and new state taxes, as well as higher property tax and transit fee.

><b>Recommended reading:</b> <a href="http://www.gothamgazette.com/article/finance/20070928/8/2301">Reviewing Federal and City Tax Cuts</a> (September 2007), <a href="http://www.gothamgazette.com/article/finance/20081128/8/2769">The Mayor's Budget Cutting Strategy</a> (November 2008)
					]]></info> 
				<alert><![CDATA[New York's already has a high tax rate that many say keeps some businesses and prospective residents away.

Do you want to make it higher at a time when the city's No. 1 industry teeters on the verge of collapse?

					]]></alert> 
			</item> 
			<item><!--incometax_wealthy--> 
				<title><![CDATA[Increase the income tax rate for high-income residents]]></title> 
				<value>603000000</value> 
				<!-- gov: state --> 
				<news></news> 
				<check>0</check> 
				<tip><![CDATA[Facing a fiscal crisis in fall 2002, Mayor Michael Bloomberg pushed through temporary increases in the city income tax that affected only higher-income New Yorkers.]]></tip> 
				<info><![CDATA[Tax the Rich: $603 million

Simply increasing the income tax rate preserves the tax's current structure. An alternative would be to change the rate system to place more of the burden on the richest New Yorkers. There are a number of proposals to do this.

One, outlined by the Independent Budget Office, would add two additional tax brackets to the current four, which, in effect, have a top rate of 3.65 percent. Under this plan, a fifth bracket would begin at $125,000 for single filers and $225,000 for joint filers with an effective rate of 3.92 percent. The top bracket, for singles with incomes of $250,00 and above and head of households making $300,000 or more, would pay an effective rate of 4.2 percent. 

Other proposals call for only increasing taxes on really rich people -- perhaps those making a million dollars of more.

The budget office figures the change it examined would affect only 7.8 percent of all city taxpayers, all of them with adjusted gross incomes above $125,000. The plan, though, would make taxes in New York even higher than they already are and could drive away some high earners. Certainly there is an irony in taxing the very rich just as there seems likely to be less of them.

><b>Recommended reading:</b> <a href="http://www.gothamgazette.com/article/finance/20070928/8/2301">Reviewing Federal and City Tax Cuts</a> (September 2007), <a href="http://www.gothamgazette.com/article/finance/20081128/8/2769">The Mayor's Budget Cutting Strategy</a> (November 2008)
					]]></info> 
			</item> 
			<item><!--state_medicaid--> 
				<title><![CDATA[Increase state Medicaid funding]]></title> 
				<value>4600000000</value> 
				<!-- gov: state --> 
				<news></news> 
				<check>0</check> 
				<tip><![CDATA[Local governments in New York have long wanted the state to pay for a greater share of Medicaid costs, but this could be a difficult time to make such a change.]]></tip> 
				<info><![CDATA[Increase State Medicaid Funding: $4.6 billion

New York State is one of a relatively small number of states that require local governments to pick up part of the state's share of the costs of Medicaid, the medical insurance program for low-income people whose costs is divided between the federal government and states. New York requires the largest local contribution of any state. 

Local governments across New York, including in New York City, have long sought to change that. One proposal would have the state pick up the costs from local governments, but then funnel some local sales tax revenues back to Albany to help the state foot the bill. 

Proponents of such an idea say this would bring New York more in line with other states and spread the burdens of medical care over the entire state. Further, they say, the state should pay the bill for Medicaid since it sets the rules for what services should be provided and to whom.

On the other hand, the state's fiscal picture appears far bleaker than that of many of its local governments. Whatever the merits of shifting the responsibility for Medicaid to Albany, this might not be the best time to do it.

><b>Recommended reading:</b> For more, see <a href="http://www.gothamgazette.com/article/health/20050802/9/1498">Making Medicaid Cheaper</a> (August 2005), <a href="http://www.gothamgazette.com/article/issueoftheweek/20050530/200/1430">Unfunded Mandates and 'Uncontrollables'</a> (May 2005)
					]]></info> 
			</item> 
			<item><!--cosmetic_medical--> 
				<title><![CDATA[Tax cosmetic medical procedures]]></title> 
				<value>65000000</value> 
				<!-- gov: state --> 
				<news></news> 
				<check>0</check> 
				<tip><![CDATA[If eye jobs and collagen injections are luxuries, some reason, shouldn't the city charge a tax on them, just as it does on other non-essential items -- and even some necessities?]]></tip> 
				<info><![CDATA[Tax Cosmetic Medicine: $65 million

Cosmetic medicine has been a booming business for the past several years but all those tummy tucks, Botox injections and facial peels are tax-free. Making them subject to the city's 4 percent sales tax could bring in $65 million -- assuming, of course, that people in this strained economy still indulge in such procedures.

					]]></info> 
			</item> 
			<item><!--capital_improve--> 
				<title><![CDATA[Tax capital improvements]]></title> 
				<value>259000000</value> 
				<!-- gov: state --> 
				<news></news> 
				<check>0</check> 
				<tip><![CDATA[There is little rhyme or reason to which home improvements are taxable and which ones are not. In these tough times, some experts have called for taxing all of them. ]]></tip> 
				<info><![CDATA[Tax Capital Improvements: $259 million 
Under New York's tax law, some services are subject to a sales tax and others are not. So, for example, homeowners must pay a tax on new landscaping but not on improvements to their property such as central air-conditioning, refinishing floors and upgrading electrical wiring. Making such improvements subject to the 4 percent city sales tax, the Independent Budget Office has calculated, could bring in an addition $259 million.
In addition, proponents believe, it would make the sales tax more uniform. It would also eliminate an inequity by making a product bought by the more affluent subject to the tax -- just as more mundane purchase are. Opponents, noting that many capital improvements are provided by small businesses, would question whether it makes sense to put another burden on these firms in the midst of a recession.
					]]></info> 
			</item> 
		</state> 
 
	</RevenuesPage> 
	
	<ComparePage> 
		<title>PLAYER VS. MAYOR</title> 
		<submit>Send your budget to Gotham Gazette</submit> 
	</ComparePage> 
	
	<SubmitPage> 
		<title>YOUR DEFICIT</title> 
		<text><![CDATA[Send us your fiscal plan and continue to get budget news from Gotham Gazette.]]></text> 
		<newsletter1>Hi, Im here</newsletter1> 
		<newsletter2>Olalal</newsletter2> 
		<newsletter3>Ahijuna</newsletter3> 
	</SubmitPage> 
	
	<ThanksPage> 
		<subtitle>Thanks for playing!</subtitle> 
		<title>Balance!</title> 
		<text><![CDATA[If balancing the budget were only this easy. Stay tuned to Gotham Gazette as we cover the real budget battle at City Hall.]]></text> 
	</ThanksPage> 
</data> 